<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-11-04T21:10:35+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><entry><title type="html">Bring a Remote Team Together on an Offsite</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/bring-your-team-together-on-an-offsite" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bring a Remote Team Together on an Offsite" /><published>2019-04-03T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-04-03T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/bring-your-team-together-on-an-offsite</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/bring-your-team-together-on-an-offsite"><![CDATA[<p>Most distributed companies bring their team members together on so-called offsites. Well, I guess you should call it an “onsite” since your remote team already work “off site” by default. Are you confused yet? Nevermind! Offsites are meant to meet, work, and play with fellow team members. Improving team bonding is a vital aspect to keep a remote team tight and connected. There are lots of ways to do this remotely, but in-person interaction is hard to mimic in a digital setup. That’s why organizing recurring offsites are the perfect solution.</p>

<p><img src="/images/mapillary-team2.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<h2 id="whats-the-goal-of-having-an-offsite">What’s the Goal of Having an Offsite?</h2>

<p>Ideally, the goal of an offsite is to get a better connection with team members through bonding and sharing social activities. While doing that, you want the team also to learn new skills by doing workshops, Q&amp;A sessions so that everyone has a chance to grow their knowledge and understanding on specific topics. One of the other key parts of offsites are team spirit and collaboration. Meeting each other is a great chance to lift the team spirit and kickstart deeper conversations around feedback, ideas, or other thoughts to improve as a team.</p>

<h2 id="are-offsites-really-necessary">Are Offsites Really Necessary?</h2>

<p>As opposed to a regular office where you see your co-workers daily, remote workers rarely see each other in real life. So, is it required to organize offsites at a remote company? No, it’s not! However, it’s stimulating to bring a team to a different place, try new things, learn about the local culture, and be emerged by a new environment. There might be an aspect of personal preference, where some people prefer digital interaction instead of real-life interaction. Nevertheless, the bodily sense of real physical presence can’t be replaced entirely through a computer. Any of these five basic senses (taste, sight, touch, smell, and sound) needs to be triggered somehow to create a more in-depth experience for ourselves and with others. These senses don’t necessarily need to be in direct relation with the other person, but could also be triggered in a particular setting when talking to someone digitally. For example, when you’re both drinking coffee while video calling, you’re both sharing an experience that trigger multiple senses. Even though you’re not physically together, besides your sight and sound being triggered, you get a more profound connection through the smell and taste of the coffee that both had while chatting. The more senses triggered, the stronger your connection will be.</p>

<h2 id="how-does-an-offsite-week-look-like">How Does an Offsite Week Look Like</h2>

<p><img src="/images/offsite-presentation.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>There are different types of schedules that remote companies apply to their offsite week. But, the goal is usually the same; to have a right balance between work, social, and relaxation time. Some teams choose to have a 50/50 balance between work and non-work social time. Others instead apply an 80/20 schedule where it’s more about working on projects together. Offsites at Mapillary are five days including travel day. On the first day, the team arrives and gathers for dinner in the evening together. The second day is all about back-to-back presentations from team leads to make sure everyone in the company is on the same page on the company’s latest and greatest. The two following days of the week are set in an <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/rebeccabagley/2014/08/18/how-unconferences-unleash-innovative-ideas/#14205902645b">unconference style</a> format, which means that there is an open schedule grid with 30-minute session slots. On the spot, everyone in the team decides to host or join a meeting or presentation on one of the slots. You can participate in any session you like even though it’s not one of your team, and whoever shows up are the right people. At the end of the week, there is time reserved for team building activities and a get-together to snap team photos. On the last day, the team sets off back home again with fresh new energy and ideas after a successful offsite week.</p>

<h2 id="being-together-is-fun-but-find-balance">Being Together Is Fun, but Find Balance</h2>

<p><img src="/images/ovi.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Offsites are often filled with lots of intense moments of interaction. It has probably been a while since you’ve last met others or you might not have met some before. It takes lots of energy and focus on spending time with people, introducing yourself, sharing thoughts, talk about projects, and do activities. There are plenty of people that are sensitive to this, and it’s good that whenever you feel you’re close to that edge, that you step back and take a break. Some find it useful to do that at the end of the day; others rather have short breaks throughout the day. Find solitude in a private space to regain energy and create balance for yourself, so that you’re ready and focused for the next moment of activities.</p>

<h2 id="team-diversity-is-key">Team Diversity Is Key</h2>

<p><img src="/images/coworkers.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>I can highly encourage creating a team of diverse people from all over the world that work in an unbiased environment that empowers empathy and deep respect for each other. Diversity should not be limited to gender, gender identity and expression, race, sexual orientation, geographical location, political and religious affiliations, cultural and/or socioeconomic background, disabilities, or age. It’s beautiful to see how a diverse team gets together and finds alignment despite their differences.</p>

<h2 id="make-everyone-feel-included">Make Everyone Feel Included</h2>

<p><img src="/images/offsite-fun.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Inclusion is the environment that you create in order to collaborate, support, and respect differences. It’s essential that during an offsite you think inclusive on all fronts and foster open dialogue and transparency about anything. Make sure that your values tie in closely with the habit of including people into conversations and activities. Don’t let anyone feel left out, and leave space for people to join, share their opinion, feel connected, and are part of the team.</p>

<p>I hope the above tips will give you an amazing offsite experience that makes your work fun, challenging, and exciting!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Most distributed companies bring their team members together on so-called offsites. Well, I guess you should call it an "onsite" since your remote team already work "off site" by default. Are you confused yet? Nevermind! Offsites are meant to meet, work, and play with fellow team members. Improving team bonding is a vital aspect to keep a remote team tight and connected. There are lots of ways to do this remotely, but in-person interaction is hard to mimic in a digital setup. That's why organizing recurring offsites are the perfect solution.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How Mapillary Works Remotely</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/how-mapillary-works-remotely" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Mapillary Works Remotely" /><published>2019-03-27T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-03-27T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/how-mapillary-works-remotely</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/how-mapillary-works-remotely"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve done an interview with <a href="https://remotewise.io">Remotewise.io</a>, which is the leading resource for remote work and they share findings from world’s top remote companies. We covered <a href="https://www.mapillary.com">Mapillary’s</a> way of working remotely and maintaining cultural values within a distributed team. You can read the full interview below.</p>

<h5 id="hello-whats-your-name-your-company-name-and-your-role-there">Hello! What’s your name, your company name and your role there?</h5>
<p>Karim Osman, Mapillary, Director of Business Operations</p>

<h5 id="can-you-give-a-brief-overview-of-the-company-background-and-what-you-guys-do">Can you give a brief overview of the company background and what you guys do?</h5>
<p>Mapillary was founded in 2013 with the goal of making street-level imagery and map data available to everyone. Our team’s mission is to build technology and tools to help understand the world’s places through images and make this data available. We want everyone to be able to use our data to make better maps, create a safer traffic environment, develop our cities, visualize places and stories, and help people in vulnerable places.</p>

<h5 id="what-percentage-of-your-company-works-remotely-and-have-you-always-been-remote-friendly-if-not-what-prompted-the-change">What percentage of your company works remotely and have you always been remote-friendly? If not, what prompted the change?</h5>
<p>100% since day one</p>

<h5 id="what-do-you-see-as-the-biggest-advantages-of-working-remotely">What do you see as the biggest advantages of working remotely?</h5>
<p>The flexibility to plan your daily working schedule in a way that makes you the happiest and most productive. And, having the ability to work with a diverse team from all around the world is a great advantage.</p>

<h5 id="what-are-the-biggest-challenges-youve-faced-and-the-obstacles-youve-overcome-if-you-had-to-start-over-what-would-you-do-differently">What are the biggest challenges you’ve faced and the obstacles you’ve overcome? If you had to start over, what would you do differently?</h5>
<p>The biggest challenge would be finding the holy grail between work and personal life. Especially when you’re not physically going away from home, the line between your work and personal life is very thin. As a matter of fact, the two seem to influence each other throughout your days, whether you like it or not. I think applying stricter rules to create a better separation between work and personal life could have helped me in the past. Also, more frequently changing environments throughout the day could bring in more balance.</p>

<h5 id="what-do-you-look-for-in-a-remote-employee-and-how-do-you-hire-for-good-company-fit">What do you look for in a remote employee and how do you hire for good company fit?</h5>
<p>We’re always looking for people that are not only passionate about our mission but also would like to go beyond that and help to create something unique. We value transparency, flexibility, honesty, and compassion, and often it takes just one or two chats with someone to get a feel if this person would fit in the rest of the team.</p>

<h5 id="what-elements-make-up-a-successful-remote-team-whats-the-trickiest-aspect-to-leading-and-managing-a-remote-team">What elements make up a successful remote team? What’s the trickiest aspect to leading and managing a remote team?</h5>
<p>I think the core values of a remote team should be precise and something everyone one thrives and strives for. At Mapillary, we focus heavily on written asynchronous communication in our daily work. The core of our communication is transparent, open, and supporting each other through trust. We default to transparency so that everyone can learn, chime in, and help out. One of the things we live by is that we engage in conversations at an early stage, we’re as clear as possible, and share any thoughts about anything. The trickiest part to lead a remote team is at the stages of transition. That’s when a team tries to scale up and at the same time is for example still small need to figure out their flows through adjusting values, tools, and communications methods to figure out what works best for your team.</p>

<h5 id="how-do-you-nurture-your-culture-and-the-personal-relationships-within-the-company">How do you nurture your culture and the personal relationships within the company?</h5>
<p>To bring team members across teams closer together, we organize weekly calls between them which we call ‘Fika’ calls. The Swedish concept of Fika essentially means making time for friends and colleagues to share a cup of coffee (or tea) and a little something to eat. In our case, we do this entirely remotely through video calls. Besides that, we yearly organize two offsites where we bring the entire team together to meet, work, and play. To us, offsites are the perfect way to nurture our team culture and improve bonding between fellow <em>‘Mapillarians’</em>.</p>

<h5 id="what-advise-would-you-give-to-a-team-just-starting-out-as-a-remote-company-or-a-team-transitioning-to-remote-work">What advise would you give to a team just starting out as a remote company or a team transitioning to remote work?</h5>
<p>A distributed framework gives you the advantage of running a global company that never sleeps. You won’t be restricted to a geographical area when hiring; you’ll have greater flexibility, and the ability to have happier employees by creating a better balance between work and personal life. Don’t be afraid to experiment with new ways of working. We’re still just seeing the beginning of remote work, so companies that go down that route have a great opportunity to shape what distributed work means to them. At Mapillary, we’ve always worked with complete transparency as it makes us faster and is realistically the only way we can operate a distributed team. Transparency and trust are two core values for us, and everyone knows it because we practice it every single day. Find out what your core values are and let it be your team’s inspiration to grow themselves and the company.</p>

<p><em>Source: <a href="https://remotewise.io/companies/mapillary/interviews/8/">Mapillary Company Interview</a></em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I've done an interview with Remotewise.io, which is the leading resource for remote work and they share findings from world's top remote companies. We covered Mapillary's way of working remotely and maintaining cultural values within a distributed team.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to Manage a Distributed Team</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/how-to-manage-a-distributed-team" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Manage a Distributed Team" /><published>2017-10-10T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-10-10T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/how-to-manage-a-distributed-team</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/how-to-manage-a-distributed-team"><![CDATA[<p>At <a href="https://www.mapillary.com/about">Mapillary</a>, we empower our team by working remotely and communicating asynchronously. Everyone is different, so we believe that the best productivity doesn’t necessarily exist between 9 to 5 in one physical location. The advantage of having a team that covers multiple time zones with a multilingual team is something that will help us excel. We’re currently (2017) a team of 32 people in 11 countries, 7 timezones, and we speak 11 different languages. Some of the team members work together in the same office or co-working space, while others work remotely from home.</p>

<p><img src="/images/mapillary.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<h2 id="how-we-work-remotely">How We Work Remotely?</h2>
<p>We focus heavily on written asynchronous communication in our daily work. The core of our communication is transparent, open, and encourages giving feedback to each other. We default to transparency so that everyone can learn, chime in, and help out. One of the things we live by is that we engage in conversations at an early stage, we’re as clear as possible, and share any thoughts about anything.</p>

<p>The tools we use are built for this purpose and help us to communicate faster and better in a distributed setup. These are the tools that keep the team running:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Slack:</strong> our chat app where we can quickly connect with each other and where all conversations happen.</li>
  <li><strong>Github:</strong> social coding for our development team and we have dedicated team boards where we have longer discussions about projects. We also track all non-developer projects (growth, operations, etc.) using Github so that it is visible for all and properly tracked.</li>
  <li><strong>Google Suite:</strong> the entire Gsuite apps like Gmail/Gdocs/Sheets help us to easily communicate and share documents internally and externally.</li>
  <li><strong>Google Hangouts and Zoom:</strong> We do recurring 1-on-1 and team video conferencing to have the ability to hear and see each other and speed up discussions.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="hiring-people-without-meeting-them-in-person">Hiring People Without Meeting Them in Person</h2>

<p><img src="/images/mapillary3.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Hiring remotely allow us to find the best talent regardless of geographical location. Working this way gives us a huge competitive advantage compared to companies that need to recruit locally or relocate people to a particular region. While hiring remotely, we’re building a range of diverse team members from all over the world, where diversity and inclusion is one of our most important focus points.</p>

<p>We recruit using global job boards (<a href="https://www.linkedin.com/jobs/">LinkedIn</a>, <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/jobs">Stack Overflow</a>, <a href="https://weworkremotely.com/">We Work Remotely</a>, <a href="https://remoteok.io/">Remote OK</a>, etc.) and interview and test candidates using the same tools that we use in our daily work. During this process we use Slack chat conversations, assignments using GitHub, and video conference for interviews or presenting candidates work. It does require mutual trust and extra research to decide it’s a right fit or not. Meeting someone psychically helps but it’s by far a deciding factor.</p>

<p>The advantage for candidates applying at <a href="http://jobs.mapillary.com">Mapillary</a> is that we allow them to live and work wherever they want, which gives them more control and flexibility in their work/life balance. The reduction in stress to commute is a revelation to team members and allows them to be more productive in return. We’re convinced that this setup makes it possible to keep team members involved and decrease turnover.</p>

<h2 id="how-we-keep-the-team-motivation">How We Keep the Team Motivation</h2>

<p><img src="/images/mapillary2.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Feeling motivated to be part of the team and working on a product you believe in is critical. We encourage feedback sharing and listen to all team members input. Praising each other and recognizing personal or team accomplishments is a vital part of how we work. Besides that, we celebrate birthdays, work anniversaries, and family member’s life events. These small celebrations help to keep the team tight and create a trusted environment where we as an employer genuinely care about employees wherever they are.</p>

<p>Twice a year we bring the team together on a company offsite where we spend a week working on projects, present work, discuss strategic topics, and getting to know each other better. Having these occasional physical meetups help team members to feel connected on a higher level. In between offsites, some teams have smaller meetups to work on specific team projects, and we have a daily/weekly/monthly meetings over video to see each other.</p>

<h2 id="how-our-distributed-model-scales">How Our Distributed Model Scales</h2>

<p>I’m proud to say that my past experiences profoundly influenced the setup that we currently have at Mapillary. I’ve seen where things went well and what didn’t when teams tried to scale their remote team. To me, the foundation period is critical when scaling a distributed team. The Mapillary base consists of deeply rooted values like Transparency, Feedback, Empowerment, and Community that keeps the team tightly together throughout the ride. Every existing or new process is built with our values and future team growth in mind.</p>

<p>The main challenges of scaling will be keeping teams as productive and manageable as possible, let team members feel motivated throughout their career path, and finding new talent.</p>

<p>When teams grow, we will likely divide them into smaller sub-teams/squads to maintain the startup atmosphere, swift communication, and feeling of ownership. The team member’s career paths will be more structured to encourage professional growth and compensation. Altogether, our foundational approach is the most efficient way to find talent, scale, and build the world’s best-distributed team.</p>

<h2 id="inspiration-from-others">Inspiration from Others</h2>

<p>There are many other companies out there that share our vision and pushing forward to this new different of working. The working remotely trend is increasing and organizations are willing to switch their habbits to thrive and survive in a fast moving industry. Here are some great resources that could help your company to transform:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://zapier.com/learn/remote-work/how-manage-remote-team/">How to Run a Remote Team</a> by Zapier</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rZ8XOcvPPTQ">The Smartest People in the World Will Work Remotely</a> by Tim Ferriss and Matt Mullenweg</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/irisleung/2017/07/31/buffer-the-tech-company-with-no-office-was-built-on-nomadic-culture/">The Tech Company With No Office</a> by Buffer</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[At Mapillary, we empower our team by working remotely and communicating asynchronously. Everyone is different, so we believe that the best productivity doesn't necessarily exist between 9 to 5 in one physical location. The advantage of having a team that covers multiple time zones with a multilingual team is something that will help us excel. We’re currently (2017) a team of 32 people in 11 countries, 7 timezones, and we speak 11 different languages. Some of the team members work together in the same office or co-working space, while others work remotely from home.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Home Office or Office Home?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/home-office-or-office-home" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Home Office or Office Home?" /><published>2017-03-23T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-03-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/home-office-or-office-home</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/home-office-or-office-home"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/laptop.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>My day usually starts just like that of any other person. I wake up, eat breakfast, dress up, and go to work. Nothing special, right? Except, in my case, all of these things are optional, not mandatory. When working from home, you don’t need to wake up early, or get dressed, or even go to the office. What!? Shower? Meh, maybe tomorrow. The entry barrier of going to work is low, because you’re already at work and you’re not physically meeting others.</p>

<p>There are many pros and cons when it comes to working from home, but some pros could be your cons and vice versa. Working from home only works well if you can find the right balance between the things that are important to you. For some, that means being surrounded by co-workers and others rather staying home being close to family. What happens when you merge these two things? Would you say you work from your home office or your office home? Well, <strong>that’s the question!</strong></p>

<h2 id="making-the-transition">Making the Transition</h2>

<p><img src="/images/home.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>When you’re new to working from home, you’ll see that the beginning has a bit of a learning curve. Your mind and body will need to adapt to this new way of flexibility and empowerment. That’s because you’re suddenly bringing your entire office life into the privacy of your home. To most of us, our home is a sacred place where we rest, play, and enjoy time with family. Even though if you have a separate working room, it will still be part of your home territory. Since you’re not physically moving away from home, the line between your work and personal life becomes thinner and thinner. As a matter a fact, the two seem to influence each other throughout your days, whether you like it or not.</p>

<p>We try to create separation by working from our home office, which is a separate room in the house. However, nowadays, most people have a laptop instead of a desktop computer and are not bound to working from the office room at home. You can make use of your entire house and can even work from the living room, the kitchen table, the bed, or the garden. Once you’ve reached this state of flexibility, your entire home becomes your office, which means you’ve officially entered the ‘office home’ level.</p>

<h2 id="the-world-is-your-office">The World is Your Office</h2>

<p>Working from home isn’t easy and there are many challenges to deal with. The empowerment doesn’t lie in working from home; it lies in being completely flexible to choice where to work from.</p>

<p>In the past, I’ve worked from co-working spaces, offices of other companies, the library, coffee shops, outdoors, in the car, and while traveling the world. All these things bring equal benefits to your balance and switching between locations is a healthy habit to have. The pace and frequency is up to you. Personally, I love having my home as the default working base, with the occasional change of working environment whenever I feel it’s needed. Having the power to explore what works best for you can be very motivating.</p>

<h2 id="keeping-it-up">Keeping It Up</h2>

<p>Motivation and discipline are two important factors of making working from home successful. Try finding ways that motivate you from waking up in the morning and spending most of your day at home. To me, working from home means being at the place and with people that I love the most. I enjoy having full control and flexibility on how I set up my schedule throughout the day. When I wake up, I start the first 30 minutes of my time doing something I like, for example watering my plants, playing with my son, or grabbing a bowl of granola with soy milk while reading news.</p>

<p>By the time I’m ready to work, I feel alive and kicking. Between work tasks, I often move around in the house to do some chores, play the guitar, or go outside for a stroll. These breaks help me to disconnect, process information and freshen up my mind when I dive back into work again.</p>

<p>There’s a huge difference between living alone or with family, and the distraction levels may vary depending on the number of people in your household. Be clear about your schedule to your fellow housemates and schedule breaks throughout your working day to spend time with family and friends. During these breaks, fully disconnect from work and be present to what you are doing. For me, that means either spending time with family, explore nature, or sit by the lake. That how I keep it up.</p>

<p><img src="/images/lake.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<h2 id="finding-the-perfect-balance">Finding the Perfect Balance</h2>

<p>It’s often hard to find the perfect balance when you’re living and working in the same space. That said, being idle while sitting/standing and staring at a screen most of the day is far from ideal. But, not having the flexibility to choose where, when, and how to schedule your day is even worse. You’re in charge and responsibility to dealing with the power of flexibility. Your personal life will interfere with your work and the other way around. If you’re not happy in one of these, then it’s almost certain that it will affect the other.</p>

<p>Give each the attention it needs and being fully present in your attention is key. Also, try one of the tips below to could help bring back the balance:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Spend the first 30 minutes of your day doing something you love, which is not work related.</li>
  <li>In the morning, write down what you will be doing today and let both your family and team know.</li>
  <li>Put extra effort in making your home feel comfortable, since you’re spending most of your day there.</li>
  <li>If you’re having a bad day for whatever reason, then try again later but don’t force yourself.</li>
  <li>Disconnect often: go out for a walk, exercise, grab a coffee. But whenever you do, be entirely disconnected and present in what you do.</li>
  <li>Add working tasks, breaks, and meetings with family/friends to your calendar. It makes it easier for you to process the switch mentally.</li>
  <li>Celebrate accomplishments and let everyone know. Yay, I showered today!</li>
</ul>

<p>In the end, it’s a matter of believing in the power of working from places where you feel most comfortable and productive, wherever and whenever that may be. Never stop experimenting with new tools, habits, exploring working environments, and changing schedules to find your perfect balance. What works for you today, might not work for you tomorrow. Stay flexible, and let both your personal and work life empower each other.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My day usually starts just like that of any other person. I wake up, eat breakfast, dress up, and go to work. Nothing special, right? Except, in my case, all of these things are optional, not mandatory. When working from home, you don't need to wake up early, or get dressed, or even go to the office. What!? Shower? Meh, maybe tomorrow. The entry barrier of going to work is low, because you're already at work and you're not physically meeting others.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Challenges Faced by Remote Workers</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/the-challenges-faced-by-remote-workers" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Challenges Faced by Remote Workers" /><published>2017-01-23T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-01-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/the-challenges-faced-by-remote-workers</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/the-challenges-faced-by-remote-workers"><![CDATA[<p>Many thanks to <a href="https://open.weadventure.org/@krsoderstrom">Kristofer Rolf Söderström</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/jeremyboom8">Jeremy Boom</a> from <a href="https://weadventure.org">WeAdventure</a> for interviewing me about working remotely. They are at the early stage of building their startup and are exploring ways to do this with a distributed team. Check <a href="https://open.weadventure.org/for-aspiring-remote-workers-5680277741a6#.faq7rkf6k">their blog</a> or read below to see what they found out:</p>

<p><img src="http://kar.im/images/sf-airport.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Access to better and faster technology has changed how we interact with the world and each other in countless ways, but there are still several aspects of life that are slower to adapt, one of them being the working day. Does the traditional 9 to 5, work from the office, day that has been dominating the work life still makes sense in our current technological age? If not, how do you structure it for you and your team according to everyone’s needs and wants?</p>

<p>I want to make a distinction because there are several professions that have never really been subject to a fixed time and location. Even some types of organisations would still not benefit from a different working routine. Instead, I’ll focus on technological companies for partly selfish reasons. Jeremy and I are currently trying to figure out what is the best approach for structuring weAdventure, and one of the questions we want to answer is how to structure the working day.</p>

<p><a href="https://medium.com/@jeremyboom8">Jeremy</a> and I have learned a lot working together and we are constantly trying to improve upon our dynamic. Currently, this involves a mix of working remotely and having face-to-face meetings every week in which we measure our progress and plan for the future. This flexibility has worked great in our favour and being able to decide when and where to work has been critical in our accomplishments. However, we are aware that what works now in a two-man team might not necessarily work in the future.</p>

<p>We decided to read about how other companies have worked on these issues. <a href="https://buffer.com/">Buffer</a> has been a good source of initial inspiration, their approach to <a href="https://open.buffer.com/">transparency</a> makes it so much easier to take in their experience and learn from it. We decided to take it a bit further and set up a call with one of their previous team members to understand that experience on an individual level.</p>

<p>We reached out to <a href="http://kar.im">Karim Osman</a>; he has worked remotely since 2010 at <a href="https://automattic.com">Automattic</a> (WordPress.com), <a href="https://buffer.com/">Buffer</a>, and currently works as Operations Director at <a href="https://www.mapillary.com">Mapillary</a>. Our conversation covered fascinating topics regarding his personal experiences. Karim was happy to share his insights (and some photos). We figured that other people might be having the sames questions as us and, in the spirit of openness, we decided to share our conversation.</p>

<p><img src="http://kar.im/images/karim-sf.jpg" alt="Enjoying the View in San Francisco" />
 <em>Karim enjoying the view in San Francisco</em></p>

<p>Here are the topics we covered:</p>

<h2 id="keeping-yourself-motivated">Keeping yourself motivated</h2>

<p>We all know that motivation is critical. This is not exclusive to remote working, but it might be more delicate to achieve than usual. Karim shared that being attracted to what you’re working on is key to feeling motivated: either the product, the team, the values and direction of the company, or being able to fulfil personal challenges and growth can be essential. For Karim, working on things that challenge him and finding personal growth in them is crucial for motivation. Complementary to this aspect is to be recognised for your work and getting a sense of appreciation for your efforts.</p>

<p>Motivation is tricky to achieve in a distributed team, but you can create an environment in which you can support each other and celebrate accomplishments. As Karim puts it: “You can even send someone a physical gift…like a chocolate bar or something physical, nowadays you can send almost anything”.</p>

<h2 id="embracing-procrastination">Embracing procrastination</h2>

<p>As anyone can imagine, procrastination seems like an obvious downside to remote work. You could be thinking to yourself how to accomplish anything with literally <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/newsround/33848745">millions cat videos on YouTube alone</a>. Karim told us that maybe it’s not so much of a bad thing. Of course, you need self-management to be able to do remote work at flexible hours, but his experience was maybe counter-intuitive.</p>

<p>“The most difficult thing when I first started working remotely was to feel guilty about having the advantage of flexible working as oppose to working fixed hours at an office. I felt like I had to do extra work in return” Karim continues, “It’s a weird thing, but sometimes you simply end up working too much and being out of balance”.</p>

<p>You should manage your time in such a way that you do not burn yourself out during the day, and procrastination might help with the much needed distraction if you are able to control it.</p>

<h2 id="routines-in-an-irregular-environment">Routines in an irregular environment</h2>

<p>The conversation flowed naturally to daily routines. According to Karim, it mostly depends in which point in your life you are now and how you interact with people closest to you, including your teammates. However, remote work gives you the possibility of changing your daily routine accordingly, and that can be a liberating experience.</p>

<p>Karim likes to work in short, intensive burst of productivity with some rest in between, but other people he knows prefer to work from 6 am to 3 pm without much rest, and then enjoy the rest of their day doing other things. There is not one routine to follow for the remote worker, you have to find your balance and embrace the flexibility you are being offered.</p>

<p>A great example of the flexibility of a remote worker is that it can also be seasonally adjusted. Prefer to work at night during summer so you can enjoy the nice weather with outside activities? No problem! Want to sleep in because it’s winter and freezing and dark outside, like here in the Nordics? No worries! However, with the caveat of your routine being compatible with your team.</p>

<h2 id="vacation-and-time-off">Vacation and time off</h2>

<p>On the topic of free-time, we quickly jumped to vacations and time off. Taking time off should be pretty straightforward and simple for everyone, but somehow it isn’t. People will have drastically different experiences in less regulated countries where time off is not guaranteed and/or paid. It’s a tricky subject, but somehow it feels like it shouldn’t be this way.</p>

<p>Remote work is no exception to the rule. It’s usual to hear that startups tend to offer unlimited vacation: take as much time off as you want and when you feel you need the most. It sounds very attractive but, as usual, reality is <a href="http://fortune.com/2016/03/10/best-companies-unlimited-vacation/">somewhat complicated</a>. In most cases, Karim mentions, you have to check with your team to make sure it won’t hurt their schedule. You could also feel pressured to not take days off, or sometimes you have the feeling that you take too much time off.</p>

<p>Company culture can have a big impact on what you feel comfortable doing. If no one else uses their vacation time and there are no reminders or friendly nudges to get it, then there’s a chance that you won’t feel up to it. You have to encourage people to do so. Some companies give employees a holiday allowance, or make friendly reminders, which Karim has experienced personally. Anything helps in that sense.</p>

<h2 id="startup-retreats">Startup retreats</h2>

<p>A good way to promote team building in a remote organisation is the startup retreat. A <a href="https://levels.io/startup-retreats/">retreat</a> is a recurring trip to bring all team members together, which has seen an increase in market lately. The right combination of work and play is vital to strengthen the relationship within teams and a retreat could help smooth this along. Karim tells us that every three or four months seems like a good threshold to see the rest of the team for most remote workers.</p>

<p>The opportunity of seeing new places and doing new things is a very appealing activity. Usually, the team does a light activity together coupled with some work, and then smaller teams can decide to do specific activities, like surfing or skydiving for the most daring.</p>

<p>Karim does mention that picking the right place for everyone goes beyond the actual location. You need to take into account the accessibility and travel time for all team members. Jet lag can be quite harsh when you have to work and play for a week straight and then head back home, straight to work. So, take a note for the sake of your team’s comfort.</p>

<h2 id="the-importance-of-trust">The importance of trust</h2>

<p>Trust is essential in any type of organisation. Trust on your teammates, the company, leadership. All of it is necessary for a well functioning project. It’s critical to generate trust and freedom for everyone involved, and this can be achieved by using the correct tools and perhaps most importantly, with choosing the right people. If you surround yourself with the right people, you can trust that they have the skills and drive to solve problems, come up with new ideas, implement them, and give feedback whenever necessary.</p>

<p>Karim tells us that transparency in a company helps build that trust in a sense that everyone is involved and has influence in what’s happening. There is, however, a need for balance in this way of internal communication. Receive too much feedback and there will be a lot of information to process that will slow down action, close yourself off and risk losing that invaluable trust.</p>

<p>We learned a lot about remote working and gained invaluable insight from Karim’s experiences, but he gave us one last piece of advise before signing off. There are no ground rules or definitive answers to remote working and distributed teams, and how to operate them. You should always be mindful of your environment, your team and their needs. Although there are best practices to follow, there is no golden rule to heed or to avoid at all costs. The tech industry evolves and changes rapidly, and in order to survive one most be able to adapt.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Many thanks to Kristofer Rolf Söderström and Jeremy Boom from WeAdventure for interviewing me about working remotely. They are at the early stage of building their startup and are exploring ways to do this with a distributed team.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Working Remotely on a Remote Farm</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/working-remotely-on-a-remote-farm" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Working Remotely on a Remote Farm" /><published>2015-10-15T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2015-10-15T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/working-remotely-on-a-remote-farm</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/working-remotely-on-a-remote-farm"><![CDATA[<p>The Internet allows you to be connected to anyone, anywhere. This is what makes working remotely in a distributed company fun because you’ll have colleagues all over the world. You’ll also spend less money on fancy office clothes, commuting with public transportation, and you can even stay in your pajamas until 3 pm. All great advantages.</p>

<p>When I first started working, remotely I felt less chained to the place I lived. I suddenly had the freedom to work and live anywhere I wanted to. I thought about moving to either San Francisco or elsewhere in the US, Canada, Australia, UK, or Sweden. Eventually, my wife and I settled in Sweden because it was not far from our home country (thus friends and family), it has a high quality of life (especially for those raising kids), and it’s not too crowded. That said, we had already been in Sweden a couple of times, and we totally loved the beautiful nature there.</p>

<p>Our first step was to try and find a house or apartment in the city. It was hard to find something affordable, and after a long search, we eventually stumbled upon a cute farm in the southern part of Sweden. The farm originated from the late 1800s and most other people considered this place as extremely remote, which was probably true.</p>

<p><img src="/images/farmie.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<h2 id="remote-farm">Remote Farm</h2>

<p>Our house in the middle of the forest yet close to a lake.
The place was surrounded by forest, lakes, and a few small villages. Going to the nearest city took about 35 minutes by car and most people owned at least two cars because public transportation was non-existing. They also calculated population density in hectares which probably said enough about the amount of people living there. Anyhow, “let’s just give it a try” is what we thought and we decided to pack our bags and move to Sweden.</p>

<p>During that time I already worked remotely so for me it didn’t matter where I lived as long as I had a computer and access to the Internet. Even if our adventure wouldn’t work out we’d have the experience of life on a farm; not many people could say that. We’d also be flexible in moving elsewhere again if needed although we didn’t plan to give up so easily.</p>

<h2 id="remote-internet">Remote Internet</h2>

<p>The first thing I was concerned about was the Internet connection, a critical aspect of the life of a remote worker. I knew that Sweden had pretty good 3G/4G coverage even in the countryside, so I explored the options. The first year we lived there I tried several different providers and located the router in various places in our house in search of the best connection. The nicest thing with these USB 3G dongles is that they allow you to connect an external antenna to improve signal strength. However, in the end, the fastest speed I got was about 10-12Mbit which for me was just enough to get the job done. A year later our area got 4G coverage that tripled the connection speed, a real gift. On sunny days, the connection was a lot faster than on rainy days. That’s why I had a backup dongle from another provider in case things go awry. Luckily our connection worked fine most of the time. Being connected allowed me to live in the middle of nowhere and still visit websites, check e-mails, and do my weekly video calls.</p>

<p><img src="/images/video-call.png" alt="" /></p>

<h2 id="extremely-remote">Extremely Remote</h2>

<p>The farm was located about 3 kilometers into the forest which meant that the only car that drove by on an average day was either the landlord, mailman, or snowplow in the winter. As you can imagine, we saw more deer, wild boars, foxes, and other animals instead of humans. Our landlord owned a dozen cows that walked around the field next to our house; this gave us the feeling that there was always something going on. Seeing animals from behind my desk was an excellent view, and I’d have to say that without them around it would have been an entirely different experience. The area was very remote but a great place if you wanted less distraction and focused on work for a while. We ended up commuting a lot because stores and facilities were not nearby. This also allowed us to get out of our isolated zone and mingle with other humans beings. Sometimes that was a good thing because it helped to break your schedule and change environments. Changing your surrounding is an important part of working remotely, it gives you new perspectives and makes you work differently. It doesn’t have to be this extreme of course but being close to nature had something special.</p>

<p><img src="/images/cows.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<h2 id="seasons-compared">Seasons compared</h2>

<p>When you live in the forest, you see the seasons change in front of your eyes. When you are not distracted by cars, people, and whatnot you’d focus more on the nature around you. You’d notice birds fly south which indicated colder weather was around the corner, leaves change color, or plants and flowers popping out of the ground. Your working schedule adapts around the season and its weather. When the weather is nice, you will spend more time outside than inside the house. For example, working on the patio with stretched legs and a laptop on your lap or just doing something else other than work. When the weather is bad, you’d stay inside, wrap yourself in a blanket, and type a lot on your keyboard to keep your hands warm. However, when you’re inside the house a lot, it’s important that you do something on the side, like a sport, a hobby, or just a daily walk outside. For us, that meant having chickens, growing vegetables, and making long walks in the forest. It’s a great way to activate your body that sits in the chair the whole day. It allows your body and mind to refuel.</p>

<p><img src="/images/farmie5.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>If you think you are ready to move elsewhere and live there for a while or just hop cities while working remotely, then I can only praise you because I know it’ll be an amazing experience. Make sure you take a look at <a href="https://nomadlist.com" target="_blank">NomadList</a> that helps you compare living costs, Internet speed, weather, and more, from places all over the world.</p>

<p>We ended up living almost three years on this farm, and it has been a life-changing experience. We’re currently back in the city, but if I would ever find a charming farmhouse again, I would move there in a heartbeat.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Internet allows you to be connected to anyone, anywhere. This is what makes working remotely in a distributed company fun because you’ll have colleagues all over the world. You’ll also spend less money on fancy office clothes, commuting with public transportation, and you can even stay in your pajamas until 3 pm. All great advantages.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The 3P’s of Startup Finances</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/the-3ps-of-startup-finances" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The 3P’s of Startup Finances" /><published>2015-09-30T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2015-09-30T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/the-3ps-of-startup-finances</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/the-3ps-of-startup-finances"><![CDATA[<p>Here you are, happily crunching the new road of your startup. Your job is to give a bird’s-eye view of the business financial health and share that with other executives. The clearer you make this for them the sooner they understand things to need change. Because after all, we want profit numbers to become or stay green. Well, then use these 3 P’s to become a master of finances: Plan, Predict, and Prepare.</p>

<h2 id="plan">PLAN</h2>

<p>First you need to plan your strategy. How are you going to tame this wild beast and stay on top of financing in your startup?. Create a flow where you follow the money:</p>

<p><img src="/images/financial-process.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Make sure you have good software that help you automate this flow. QuickBooks is a great piece of software that can help you automate the process of importing and tracking expenses, run payroll, pay taxes, and create reports.</p>

<p>No matter what you use, make sure it’s automated and then let it run by itself. Now you can spend your energy on these two questions: where is the money coming from? And where does it go to?</p>

<p><strong>Where does money come from?</strong></p>

<p>Knowing where the money comes from gives you a greater understanding of its value. Do investors fund your startup? Or doesn’t it need funding because it’s already profitable? You have to realize there’s a big difference between being funded or not because expectations differ depending on the amount of money involved. Investors always expect a higher growth rate, which makes sense because they want to see 10x, 50x, or 100x ROI (return on investment) within the next 5-10 years. The high ROI from investors may sound unnatural, but it’s not unusual in startup land.</p>

<p>If your startup is already profitable and doesn’t require extra funding, then you can focus more on natural growth as there is less pressure from external parties. That doesn’t mean you don’t have to grow fast, though. Anyhow, both can either lead to success or destruction. That brings us to our next question.</p>

<p><strong>Where does the money go to?</strong></p>

<p>Now here is when things get tricky. Let’s say there is capital available for either sales or funding. If the expenses are higher than the MRR (monthly recurring revenue), then clean up your desk and pack your backpack because your startup will die soon. If the burn rate of your venture capital is too high, then leave that bag and start running because the ‘angry investors apocalypse’ is about to happen. We need to have a deep understanding of where the money io. Make sure it’s well spent and then follow it carefully.</p>

<p>For most startups the monthly expenses looks a bit like this, from high to low:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Wages</li>
  <li>Employee benefits</li>
  <li>Hosting</li>
  <li>Advertising / Marketing</li>
  <li>Legal</li>
  <li>Taxes</li>
  <li>Dues &amp; Subscriptions</li>
  <li>Rent or Lease / Office expenses</li>
  <li>Other expenses</li>
</ul>

<p>The order of these expenses depend on the stage your startup is in. Especially in the first period legal expenses can go sky-high so always ask for an estimation beforehand. The ‘other expenses’ item could be travel, insurance, meal and entertainment, or bank charges.</p>

<h2 id="predict">PREDICT</h2>

<p>Instead of running behind the facts and panicking when expenses suddenly go up, try learning how to code so that you can create a more realistic forecast or budget. Even though software like QuickBooks allows you to crunch balance sheets and ledgers, it does not focus too much on that. If you are serious about analysing financial health, then you should consider using analysis software like <a href="https://fathomhq.com" target="_new">Fathom</a> or Microsoft’s <a href="https://powerbi.microsoft.com" target="_new">Power BI</a>. These two are crazy powerful, and they can import and automatically sync all your financial data from QuickBook, Excel, and more. Fathom allows you to set financial KPI’s (Key Performance Indicators) to show your financial health. You can then compare the KPI’s with targets set in your budget.</p>

<p><img src="/images/fathom.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>If you want a tool that gives you a beautiful visualization of your finances, then Power BI is your friend. It shows you an elegant dashboard filled with useful metrics and allows you to connect non-financial apps as well. All your data in one place.</p>

<p><img src="/images/powerbi.png" alt="" /></p>

<h2 id="prepare">PREPARE</h2>

<p>Finally! You’re a financial mastermind now. You’ve planned your flow, predicted the future, and now you are crossing your fingers hoping things will go as planned. However, you always need to be prepared for unexpected events. Or as they say: hope for the best, prepare for the worst. A good way to do this is to do such activities part of your budget. You could make specific budgets larger or create dedicated resources for the unexpected. In either case tight is not right.</p>

<p>Always stay flexible in case of drastic changes, keep your eyes open for new products or services that help improve your workflow, and last but not least don’t get too comfortable! 💸</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Here you are, happily crunching the new road of your startup. Your job is to give a bird’s-eye view of the business financial health and share that with other executives. The clearer you make this for them the sooner they understand things to need change. Because after all, we want profit numbers to become or stay green. Well, then use these 3 P's to become a master of finances: Plan, Predict, and Prepare.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to Survive Remote Communication</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/how-to-survive-remote-communication" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Survive Remote Communication" /><published>2015-09-28T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2015-09-28T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/how-to-survive-remote-communication</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/how-to-survive-remote-communication"><![CDATA[<p>Communication has always been the key to our success and our survival. This is true for our species and is just as true for our businesses. Companies live and die by how well they communicate. So, how do we foster productive relationships in a workplace that spans the globe?</p>

<h2 id="remote-has-never-felt-so-close">“REMOTE” HAS NEVER FELT SO CLOSE</h2>

<p>At <a href="https://lookback.com">Lookback</a>, we embrace the distributed workplace. Working from home, the office, the park or the beach, being a night owl or an early bird, the lifestyle freedom is amazing. I once did a trip from Amsterdam to Egypt, and then China to Kuala Lumpur, to Singapore, to Australia, to Fiji, to the United States and back to Amsterdam, all still on the clock. It felt like a honeymoon with my laptop. Seriously, people say this a lot, but you have to experience it to understand just how empowering it is to be the only person calling the shots in how, when, and where you work.</p>

<p><img src="/images/island.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<h2 id="the-right-tools-for-the-job">THE RIGHT TOOLS FOR THE JOB</h2>

<p>Building this culture is fundamentally about attitude, but there are tools out there that can help you create this awesome new environment.</p>

<p><strong>This is what we use at <a href="https://lookback.io" target="_new">Lookback</a>:</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://flowdock.com">Flowdock</a> for direct and threaded text chats including quick file sharing.</li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com">Github</a> for social coding and we’ve recently been experimenting with using Github Issues as our internal forum for discussions lengthier than we have on Flowdock.</li>
  <li><a href="https://trello.com">Trello</a> to organize projects and tasks for our weekly product improvements and current releases.</li>
  <li><a href="https://sqwiggle.com">Sqwiggle</a> to video chat and simply see each other during our work day.</li>
  <li><a href="https//drive.google.com">Google Drive</a> for writing and sharing documents or those darn TPS reports.</li>
</ul>

<p>While these may work great for us now, our communication needs may change. We are always looking for better tools, better ways of bringing us closer together while maintaining our freedom to choose how we work. Currently, we use some separate tools to facilitate different modes of communication and collaboration, but perhaps there could be one single tool to rule them all? We haven’t settled on one definite and ultimate way, and I think that’s a good thing; stay hungry, stay foolish, as the bard says.</p>

<h2 id="experiment-and-break-the-cycle">EXPERIMENT AND BREAK THE CYCLE</h2>

<p>Working remotely is not without its challenges. The ability to work from anywhere can be a pitfall if you don’t allow yourself NOT to work from anywhere. By experimenting with different workflows, I discovered that breaking the cycle is one of the most important things to do. By breaking it I mean stop doing what you do and do something else for a dedicated amount of time, something unrelated to work. Daily exercise breaks (like running or yoga) combined with an occasional trip away helps you overcome inactivity and isolation.</p>

<p>The key to addressing challenges is to have that right culture, to establish an energy within the team where we strive to connect with one another, both at work and socially. There’s no substitute for group conversation and just shooting the breeze with your workmates; it’s what we are born to do, and it’s what we need at the most fundamental level to be happy. On top of this, you need trust for a distributed team to work: we are all adults here, and we trust each other to make the right decisions. That means we help each other when we see there is a need, and we never hesitate to reach out if we need a hand. That’s the kind of environment that empowers me; that’s how I will survive and thrive this remote adventure.</p>

<p><em>Originally posted at <a href="https://lookback.io/blog/how-to-survive-remote-communication" target="_blank">https://lookback.io/blog/how-to-survive-remote-communication</a></em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Communication has always been the key to our success and our survival. This is true for our species and is just as true for our businesses. Companies live and die by how well they communicate. So, how do we foster productive relationships in a workplace that spans the globe?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Good CFO’s Know How To Code</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/good-cfos-know-how-to-code" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Good CFO’s Know How To Code" /><published>2015-09-26T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2015-09-26T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/good-cfos-know-how-to-code</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/good-cfos-know-how-to-code"><![CDATA[<p>As CFO at a tech startup, your job is to plan, implement, manage, and control all financial-related activities of the company. This contains responsibility for accounting, finance, forecasting, strategic planning, legal, negotiations, relationships, and compliances. You are not involved in any of the product building, design, system administration, support, HR, or sales. However, all these parts are equally important for bringing value and revenue to your company.</p>

<h2 id="learn-how-to-code">LEARN HOW TO CODE</h2>

<p>You already know the ‘Code of Finance’, you are good with numbers, and you are on top of your game. Now it’s time to learn the Code of Developers, Designers, Sales, Metrics, Sysadmins, etc. You see, if you don’t genuinely understand how others code things in your company, then you won’t be able to excel at your job. You have to know the tech behind the tech. Become a coder of all departments.</p>

<h2 id="how-to-get-started">HOW TO GET STARTED</h2>

<p>It’s simple, connect with others across teams as much as possible. They are your pool of knowledge; you just have to start fishing. Learn from them, ask them to teach you about their work, and try to understand where their decisions are coming from. The more you know about what they do and why, the better you will be able to understand the story behind numbers on your balance sheet.</p>

<p><strong>Review and Rewind</strong></p>

<p>How does the design of our products affect revenue? How does support influent upgrade cancellations? How come expenses go up when our site has downtime? Team leads don’t think about income; they think about managing teams or improving products. Instead of throwing budgets at them, share your vision instead and understand theirs. Once you get that, then you can discuss appropriate changes to improve financial outcome.</p>

<p><strong>Never Stop Learning</strong></p>

<p>Heck, take a marketing, sales, or even JavaScript workshop from colleagues if that helps you better understand certain expenses. If you’re in one position, it doesn’t mean you don’t need to learn more about the other ones out there. Suck in as much information from your pool as possible for understanding the company’s financial wealth. Only then you can create a more realistic forecast.</p>

<p>Don’t cut the server expenses budget if it’s going through the roof. Instead, let developers explain what value, for example, the AWS cloud is to the business. Let them show you their most important piece of code. From there you can then start optimizing and exploring ways to decrease monthly costs.</p>

<p>Never stop learning and always rewind back to finance.</p>

<h2 id="why-just-cfos">WHY JUST CFO’S?</h2>

<p>The philosophy I’ve just explained doesn’t come naturally for most CFO’s. They have an MBA background and are head deep in just numbers and operations. They know what the numbers mean but not always where they come from, as opposed to CEO’s and COO’s who already firmly believe in this philosophy since day one.</p>

<p>As the finance person, you’re the key player of these musketeers. Without your hard work, the business will eventually die, one way or another.</p>

<p>Open your mind, be curious about every layer within the company, embrace the different codes, and aim to become a stellar CFO: <em>Coder &amp; Financial Officer</em> :)</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As CFO at a tech startup, your job is to plan, implement, manage, and control all financial-related activities of the company. This contains responsibility for accounting, finance, forecasting, strategic planning, legal, negotiations, relationships, and compliances. You are not involved in any of the product building, design, system administration, support, HR, or sales. However, all these parts are equally important for bringing value and revenue to your company.]]></summary></entry></feed>